A Guide to the Papers of Notable Virginia Families, 1763-1866
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Notable Virginia Families, 1763-1866
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
2988
This collection contains 610 items (4 Hollinger boxes, 1.5 linear shelf feet.)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were purchased by the University of Virginia Library for the Tracy W. McGregor Library on August 3, 1948, from James Lewis Hook of Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.
Scope and Content Information
The Papers of Robert Beverley
The papers of Robert Beverley, executor of the estate of William Augustine Washington, 1783-1831, 42 items, includes letters, 1809-1810, from British minister plenipotentiary Francis James Jackson (1770- 1814) concerning the recall of David M. Erskine following the Chesapeake-Leopard affair, Jackson's peace initiatives, and protests against a renewed embargo; and an indenture and bond for Loudoun and Jefferson County land signed by Ferdinando Fairfax. Most of the papers are concerned with Beverley's settlement of the estate of William Augustine Washington. Correspondents include John Tayloe Lomax, Thomas B. Barton, Thomas Gresham, William Brooke, William Macfarlane, Phillip Pendleton Barbour, Briscoe Gerard Baldwin, Daniel Sheffey, Bushrod Washington, and Sarah Tayloe Washington.
The Richard Henry Lee Estate Papers
The papers of Richard Henry Lee, 1763-1810, ca. 50 items, chiefly concern the settlement of Richard Henry Lee's estate, containing individual accounts with the estate and accounts of sales of stock and household furnishings held at Chantilly and at Westmoreland Court House, 1794-1795. It also includes the will of Arthur Lee and accounts of John Brockenbrough with Richard Henry Lee pertaining to his estate and a letter, 1785, of Ludwell Lee. Papers of Henry Lee include letters of John Potts to Lee regarding William Augustine Washington's claim against Maryland, the case of Russell vs. Henry Lee, and General Henry Lee's plea for help to Bushrod Washington following his imprisonment for debts.
The Lewis Family Papers
The papers of the Lewis family, includes the letters and business papers of George Washington's nephew, Lawrence Lewis, many of them related to the settlement of the General's estate and to farming operations at Mount Vernon after his death. Included are a receipt to Martha Washington from an Alexandria bank, and correspondence of Lorenzo Lewis (1803-1847), son of Lawrence Lewis, as a student in Philadelphia, among which is a letter commenting on the election of 1824, and at "Audley," his plantation in Virginia, after his marriage. Other topics include the War of 1812, the Embargo and related issues, national politics, the running of a sugar plantation in Louisiana, slavery, emancipated slaves, and family news.
The Madison Family Papers
The papers of the Madison family, 1768-1866, 153 items, include correspondence of James Madison; draft of Madison's second inaugural address; notes of a conversation between James Madison and Colonel Beckwith concerning the Northwest Indians; the Embargo; letter with notation from Thomas Jefferson; papers relating to Montpelier and its inhabitants, Madison's opinions on money, nullification, the convention with France concerning shipping, the British navy and impressment, and Andrew Jackson's participation in the War of 1812.
They also include the personal and business correspondence of Dolley Madison concerning the settlement of Madison's estate, the sale of Montpelier, and the use of the Madison papers, including deeds of gift, indentures, several versions of Dolley Madison's will, lists of books and paintings of Montpelier, resolution of the House of Representatives concerning Dolley Madison, papers relating to her estate, letters and documents of her son John Payne Todd, mostly relating to gifts from his mother; and letters, 1857-1866, from William Cabell Rives to J.C. McGuire pertaining to Madison's papers and biography.
James Madison's correspondents include James Barbour, John H. Cocke, George Dallas, Joseph Delaplaine, Lyman Draper, William Duane, Ferdinando Fairfax, John Forbes, Augustus John Foster, Alexander Hamilton, Jr., William Jarvis, Robert Levington, James Madison, Sr., John Mason, James Monroe, John Randolph of Roanoke, Elijah Russell, Thomas Ritchie, Fulwar Skipwith, David Triplett, and Isaac Winston.
Dolley Madison's correspondents include Augustus, Count of Wurttenburg, Mary Bagot, Robert Brent, John Campbell, M.K. Crittenden, Mrs. Albert Gallatin, James Hoban, L. de Kantzou, Thomas Law, Ann Maury, Annie Mifflin, Thomas Ritchie, Judith Page Walker Rives, Maria Mayo Scott, and William Tudor.
Other topics include the War of 1812, social occasions, the financial difficulties of John Payne Todd, diplomatic news and events, State Department matters, political appointments, the University of Virginia, the sale and publication of the papers of James Madison, national politics, the Louisiana Territory, state's rights, federalism, and slavery.
The Papers of the Washington Family
Letters and business papers of George Washington's nephew, Judge Bushrod Washington, and his cousin, William Augustine Washington, including correspondence, accounts, bills, indentures, and other papers, chiefly concerning the settlement of the estates of George Washington, William Augustine Washington, and Thomas Turner, but also including correspondence pertaining to the estates of Richard Henry Lee, Arthur Lee, and General Henry Lee. Also, letters, 1783, from Edmund Randolph re legislative procedures in the Virginia General Assembly including a bill to pay off the Army debt. Also mentioned are slaves freed by George Washington, western land claims, the War of 1812, negotiations with merchants from Lisbon, Portugal, handled for Congress in 1785-1786 by Philip Mazzei, legislative matters in Virginia, the Dismal Swamp Canal Company, plants for the garden at Mount Vernon, and agriculture in Virginia and Louisiana. Also present is the business correspondence of a Baltimore merchant, James Cox, at the conclusion of the War of 1812.
Organization
This collection has been divided into five small series based upon the basic family involved, with correspondents arranged alphabetically within each series, including: Series I: The Papers of Robert Beverley (Box 1); Series II: The Richard Henry Lee Estate (Box 1); Series III: The Lewis Family Papers (Box 1-2); Series IV: The Madison Family Papers (Boxes 2-4); and Series V: The Washington Family Papers (Box 4). This guide will briefly summarize each series (pages 1-4) but a fuller item description will follow in the folder listing beginning on page five.
Contents List
- The Papers of Robert Beverley
  - Briscoe G. Baldwin to Robert Beverley 1826 June 14 (Box 1)
    cannot represent him in the suit brought against him, as executor of William A. Washington (1757-1810), by Andrew Parks because he is presently representing Mrs. Parks.
  - Philip Pendleton Barbour to Robert Beverley 1820-1821 (Box 1)
    discusses the lawsuits against Beverley concerning the Washington estate.
  - Thomas B. Barton to Robert Beverley 1818-1822 (Box 1)
    Reports on his progress in representing him at Fredericksburg in the case of Washington vs Beverley; sends a copy of the account of William A. Washington with his father, S. Barton (1821 April 18); and summarizes the case, "I have at length completed my report in the case of Washington vs Beverley & few more troublesome or voluminous cases have been returned to this court" (1822 May 17.
  - Robert Beverley to Mrs. Sarah (Tayloe) Washington (1765-1834), widow of William Augustine Washington (copy) 1831 August 6 (Box 1)
    discusses the debt she is said to owe to the estate of her late husband and other related financial matters.
  - Robert Beverley to James Wilson (copy) 1825 November 17 (Box 1)
    Writes concerning the payment of his fee in the Washington vs Andrew Parks case.
  - William Brooke to Robert Beverley 1814-1816 (Box 1)
    Advises him of a claim from Henry S. and Thomas Warner against the estate of William A. Washington and has not heard from Mr. Thompson concerning Washington's land.
  - John Campbell to Robert Beverley 1819 February 25 (Box 1)
    discusses the claims of his client against the William A. Washington estate.
  - Ralph Edmonds to Robert Beverley 1816 August 7 (Box 1)
    Asks if it is possible for Beverley to pay a bond he holds against the William A. Washington estate.
  - Thomas Gresham, Jr. to Robert Beverley 1814 June 20 (Box 1)
    discusses the settlement of the judgment of Mr. Payne's administrator against Beverley which cannot be settled until the money is sent.
  - Noblet Herbert to Robert Beverley 1821 August 23 (Box 1)
    Informs Beverley that Judge Bushrod Washington has left Alexandria for the Shenandoah Springs in Jefferson County and then Philadelphia, not returning until November;and that Judge Washington was never the executor for the estate of Corbin Washington (1765-1800) but functioned as the guardian of his children.
  - Francis James Jackson (1770-1814), to Robert Beverley 1809-1810 (Box 1)
    British minister plenipotentiary sent to Washington in 1809 upon the recall of David Montagu Erskine, which he discusses along with the need to promote the common welfare of both countries (1809 November 30); discusses the measure brought up in the House of Representatives which he can call by no other name than "embargo in disguise" more interfering in trade than the former embargo and warns of the United States being excluded from European ports and blockaded (1809 December 23); expects to leave soon for New York where he will wait for a ship to take him back to England and warns about the influence of the violent party in America who do not care about good relations with England (1810 January 10); and discusses the possible passage of Macon's Bill No. 2 (1810 February 1).
  - John Taylor Lomax (1781-1862) to Robert Beverley 1811 January 14 (Box 1)
    Gives his advice about "ancient open claims" against the William A. Washington estate.
  - William MacFarlane to Robert Beverley 1817 February 12 (Box 1)
    Writes concerning the sale of mortgaged land in Stafford County in the case of Russell vs Lee.
  - William Maffitt to Robert Beverley 1819 February 10 (Box 1)
    Teacher of William Washington requests funds for the furtherance of his education.
  - Daniel Sheffey (1770-1830) to Robert Beverley 1826 April 19 (Box 1)
    Since he has been retained on behalf of Andrew Parks (1770-1836) in the case concerning the William A. Washington estate, he cannot help Beverley.
  - Samuel Templeman to Robert Beverley 1815 April 10 (Box 1)
    The ending of the War of 1812 should now permit them to conclude the case concerning the William A. Washington estate and asks Beverley to deliver up his books and records about his administration.
  - Bushrod Washington (1785-1831) to Robert Beverley 1812 and 1818 (Box 1)
    Gives notice to take a deposition; discusses the mortgage on Laurel Grove.
  - James Wilson to Robert Beverley 1825 and 1828 (Box 1)
    Has asked John H. Peyton to assist him in presenting Beverley's case before the court in the Greenbrier Courthouse which he discusses regarding the William A. Washington estate.
  - Bonds and Indentures, involving William Herbert, Robert Patton, Ferdinando Fairfax, and Peter R. Beverley 1812 and 1820 (Box 1)
- Richard Henry Lee Estate Papers
  - Arthur Lee - Accounts with John Brockenbrough and Ralph Wormeley 1791-1794 (Box 1)
  - Arthur Lee - Will (copy), with codicil, October 25, 1792 1792 July 27 (Box 1)
  - L. Hollingsworth to Henry Lee (copy) 1795 October 5 (Box 1)
    The claim of William A. Washington upon the state of Maryland.
  - 1798 (Box 1)
    Writes concerning the claim of William A. Washington upon the state of Maryland and its settlement.
  - William Russell vs. Henry Lee [ca. 1801] (Box 1)
    A suit concerning land in Stafford County, Virginia.
  - Henry Lee to Judge [Bushrod] Washington 1810 February 3 (Box 1)
    Asks for help while in the Spotsylvania Courthouse jail for debt.
  - Ludwell Lee to General [?] 1785 July 27 (Box 1)
    Presently working as a county court lawyer, regrets letting their correspondence discontinue, sorry to hear the General has resigned his public service because men of integrity are still urgently needed, "we have brought our bark on shore but she is not yet safely moored".
  - Richard Henry Lee Estate Accounts with Colonel Thomas Chilton; William Forbes & Company; Henderson, Ferguson & Gibson; Mathews, Goldthwait & Company; James Maury; Hugh Quinlan; Thomas Sanford; Dr. Thomas Thomson; Jane Wigley; and Ralph Wormeley ca. 1763-1795 (Box 1)
  - Richard Henry Lee Estate - Miscellaneous 1794-1797 (Box 1)
    Includes the receipts and accounts of his executors, William A. and Corbin Washington.
  - Richard Henry Lee Estate - Sales at "Chantilly" and Westmoreland County Courthouse 1794-1795 (Box 1)
- Lewis Family Papers
  - George Washington Bassett (1800-1878) to Lawrence Lewis (1767-1839) 1832 July 3 (Box 2)
    Writes that an injunction has been brought against the Loyal Company by some French claimants; although he obtained the permission of the committee, he was unable to fulfill the request of Lewis concerning his mother's removal due to the opposition of Mr. Gordon; and the foundation for the monument of [Mary Washington] was in the process of being laid.
  - Charles Bennett to Lawrence Lewis 1822-1835 (Box 2)
    Charles Bennett may be a partner in the business firm of Bennett & Watts, merchants of Alexandria, and these letters discuss the purchase of various articles, such as flour, and other business, including the possible suit of Eliza Custis against her former husband, Thomas Law (1832 February 23); asks for help in getting Mr. Rodgers, son-in-law of Eliza Parke Custis Law, to pay a debt (1833 February 25); mentions an attack on President Andrew Jackson by Lt. Randolph taken up by the grand jury (1833 May 6); and the necessity of Lewis owning at least a share in the [Bank of Potomac ?] if he is to remain on the Board of Directors (1835 January 22).
  - Carter Beverley to Lawrence Lewis 1807 September 22 (Box 2)
    directions concerning the business affairs of Miss Lilly Harve.
  - William Booth to Lawrence Lewis 1812 April 11 (Box 2)
    Lists the trees he is shipping to Lewis by packet boat from Baltimore.
  - William Brent to Lawrence Lewis 1828 (Box 2)
    Writes concerning the claim of Lewis against the British government for the value of a slave, Michael [Lee?], who was carried away by the British, requesting his surname so the log books and records of various ships can be searched.
  - William Burnett to Alexander Moore 1842 December 1 (Box 2)
    Writes concerning the settlement of the estate of George Washington and the mortgage of Burdet Ashton.
  - Edward George Washington Butler (1800-1878) to his father-in-law, Lawrence Lewis 1825-1835 (Box 2)
    Asks for permission to marry Frances, the daughter of Lawrence Lewis (1825 March 30); mentions invitations from Andrew Jackson to visit the Hermitage in Tennessee and discusses his chances in the election (1826 July 30); the birth of a son, his belief that a Jacksonian, Mr. Campbell of Ohio, might be elected to the Senate (1826 December 13); discusses the prospects for his Louisiana property, the safe arrival of Angela and Mrs. Lawrence, and the difficulties of Henry Clay in Kentucky (1827 August 30); his confidence in the promise of the sugar market and the return trip of Angela and Mrs. Lawrence to Virginia (1827 October 30); the possible purchase of a plantation with his brother-in-law, Mr. Bell (1827 December 14); the promise of racing sport with his dogs at Mount Vernon by Bushrod Washington (1828 October 27); description of his trip to Canada (1829 August 27); writing from the plantation at Herville, Louisiana, he discusses the sugar crop and new laws in Louisiana prohibiting the introduction of slaves into the state for immediate sale (1831 December 18); discusses the sugar crop and the birth of a daughter (1832 March 7, August 29); loading his molasses and sugar on the brig Malaga bound for Philadelphia (1833 January 28); discusses the Tariff Bill, John Calhoun and Henry Clay, the Resolutions of 1798-1799, nullification, and Andrew Jackson (1833 March 15); legal and logistical difficulties in purchasing slaves as field hands for his plantation and details of his debt to the Bank of Louisiana (1833 April 10 and May 6); the purchase of slaves at Richmond, Virginia (1833 June 11 and July 25); the good crop of sugar cane (1833 June 17); the ravages of cholera in Louisiana especially among the slaves (1833 July 25); the birth of Caroline Butler prior to the arrival of the midwife (1834 August 23); a news clipping concerning the slavery prohibition in Louisiana attached to letter describing his sugar crop (1834 November 8); and his negotiations with the Union Bank for a loan (1835 February 25).
  - Frances Parke (Lewis) Butler (1799-1875) to her father, Lawrence Lewis 1827-1835 (Box 2)
    Writing from Cincinnati, Ohio, shares her disappointment at his failure to visit them and her hopes of Butler securing a sugar plantation in Louisiana (1827 August 12); and her continued concern over her father's health and lack of visitation (1832 May 27; 1833 August 11).
  - Elizabeth (Lewis) Carter (1765-1830?) to her brother, Lawrence Lewis 1825 June 17 (Box 2)
    Mentions her daughters, Otwayanna Carter (1805-?) and Eleanor Custis Lewis Carter Brown (1800-1845), and her son-in-law, George Tucker, and son, William Farley Carter (1797-?).
  - Otwayanna Carter to Lawrence Lewis 1829 January 31 (Box 2)
    Her mother upset by the death of Uncle Robert Lewis of Fredericksburg, and notes the declining health of her mother and Henry Brown.
  - 182[8?] August 29 (Box 2)
    Writes concerning news of home.
  - Dr. H.P. Daingerfield to Lawrence Lewis 1832-1834 (Box 2)
    Writes concerning his and Lewis' health, their trouble with gout, and his interest in the family (1832 June 21); prevented from visiting by the sudden illness of one of his slaves (1832 July 11); describes the bad weather and its effect on Alexandria and his happiness that Lewis was in Louisiana avoiding it (1834 January 14 and March 13).
  - Thomas Davison to Lawrence Lewis 1820-1833 (Box 2)
    Writes about the estate of George Washington and a share in the Potomac Company (1820 December 14, et al); mentions a religious revival, the poor health of Charles Lewis (1775-1829), the brother of his wife, [Nancy Davison?], and Charles' oldest daughter, who was handicapped from birth, the alcoholism of her brother, Robert Lewis (1782-?), and the insanity of Mrs. Iredale (d.1833), the third daughter of Alexander Eliot Spotswood (1829 February 15); the death of Charles Lewis and his daughter, Mrs. Iredale placed in the asylum in Lexington, Kentucky, and her children dispersed (1829 November 21; 1830 May 8); and the death of his daughter, who married Dr. Hansford, and the death of Mrs. Iredale (1833 December 6).
  - P. Doddridge to Lawrence Lewis 1832 April 24 (Box 2)
    Asks if Archibald McClean is indebted to the estate of George Washington.
  - Eliza B. and Ferdinando Fairfax to Lawrence Lewis 1817 June 20 (Box 2)
    Mentions business related to the Shannon Mill and an agreement with D. Musselman.
  - 1805-1837, n.d. (Box 2)
    Account for corn for "free Negroes," emancipated slaves from the Washington estate (1814 December 21); the sale of various slaves (1835 January 18); the beating of Mercer by Judge [John?] Scott, 1781-1850, with his stick (n.d.); and other business matters.
  - Zachariah Gardner to Lawrence Lewis 1815 March 3 (Box 2)
    Account for corn for "free Negroes," emancipated slaves from the Washington estate.
  - James E. Heath to Lawrence Lewis 1836 October 21 (Box 2)
    An auditor in Richmond, discussing back taxes.
  - 1823 June 18, n.d. (Box 2)
    concerning the estate of George Washington.
  - James Kennedy to Lawrence Lewis 1815 May 11 (Box 2)
    Receipt on his account, mentions the return of peace following the War of 1812, and mentions having the concluding number of Alexander Wilson's Ornithology available.
  - William Kercheval to Lawrence Lewis 1800-1802 (Box 2)
    Kercheval, the agent of Lewis, discusses the daily financial affairs of Lewis' farm in Frederick County, Virginia, including squatters, need for horses, debts, crops, etc. (all letters) and the case of Peck vs Lewis (1801 June 9); the illness of his slaves and activities of Elijah Kercheval (1802 March 10).
  - William F. Krumbhaar to Lawrence Lewis 1834 May 23 (Box 2)
    Arrangements for the return voyage of Mrs. Lewis and Angela from New Orleans.
  - Andrew Lewis to Lawrence Lewis 1813 and 1818 (Box 2)
    concerning an agreement between, Andrew Lewis, Lawrence Lewis and Andrew Parks (1813) and attempts to obtain salt from saltwater (1818).
  - Charles Lewis to Lawrence Lewis 1821 May 27 (Box 2)
    Writes concerning a share in the Potomac Company and his handicapped daughter.
  - n.d. (Box 2)
    Writes with concerns about taking care of her slaves.
  - Ellen H. Lewis to Lawrence Lewis 1825-1834 (Box 2)
    Ellen, the widow of his brother, Howell, thanks him for the check (1825 December 27); writes of her finances (1827 January 26); and gives him news of her children (1834 September 24).
  - Gabriel Lewis to his uncle, Lawrence Lewis 1802-1808 (Box 2)
    Writes concerning his financial affairs and the estate of George Washington.
  - George and Robert Lewis to Lawrence Lewis 1802 October 15 (Box 2)
    discusses the sale of Columbia Bank stock, part of the estate of George Washington.
  - Howell Lewis to Robert Lewis 1815 and 1817 (Box 2)
    Advises him not to sell his land (1815 August 31); and furnishes examples of the price of land in recent sales in the area (1817 April 19).
  - Lawrence Lewis to Colonel Joseph Erwin 1827-1828 (Box 2)
    Thanks him for collecting a debt for him in Louisiana and other financial matters.
  - Lawrence Lewis to Jonathan Janney 1815 July 25 (Box 2)
    Wool being sent to him.
  - 1825 February 1, n.d. (Box 2)
    Account for corn, house, and wood furnished the "free Negroes," emancipated slaves from the George Washington estate and other matters pertaining to the estate.
  - Lawrence Lewis to James Moore 1813 June [18] (Box 2)
    Full description of the quality of his wool.
  - Lawrence Lewis to Judge Bushrod Washington 1823 January 30 (Box 2)
    Writes concerning money to be paid to the trustees of Mrs. E. P. Custis.
  - Lawrence Lewis to John Wickham 1831 April 28 (Box 2)
    Inquires about two court cases involving the late Bushrod Washington at the chancery court at Clarksburg.
  - Lorenzo Lewis to Eleanor Parke Custis Lewis [1825] May 8 (Box 2)
    Provides information about the character and family of Benedict Dorsey.
  - 1825-1834, n.d. (Box 2)